Guide to the Payson J. Treat Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Payson J. Treat papers
1907-1945
SC0436
Treat, Payson J. (Payson Jackson), 1879-1972
3.5 Linear feet
Papers include articles and lectures, c. 1910-1940, pertaining to the politics and history of the Far East and World War I; class lecture notes, 1907-1945, and papers by students, 1911-1943; correspondence, bibliographies, and records pertaining to book purchases for the Stanford University Libraries; and miscellaneous correspondence, bibliographies, and book reviews.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Mrs. Virginia Davis, 1992 and 2004.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Payson Jackson Treat, a pioneer in Far Eastern studies, lived from 1879 to 1972. A native of New York City, he earned his A.B. from Wesleyan University in 1900, and began teaching at Barnard School while working on his A.M. at Columbia. In 1903, he came to Stanford to work with Professor Max Farrand in the history department, and was appointed an instructor at Stanford in 1905. He received Stanford's first Ph.D. in history in 1910 with his dissertation, The National Land System, 1785-1820.
In 1906, Dr. Jordan, intrigued with the Far East, created a professorship in Far Eastern history and appointed Payson Treat to fill it. Dr. Jordan also planned for him a leave of absence from 1906-07 to visit the Orient and Australasia. This was to be the first of five extended trips to the Far East. On these trips, he not only took the opportunity to become one of America's leading scholars on the Orient, but he also began to gather materials from the East for the Stanford libraries.
During his career, he published numerous books and articles on the Far East. He participated in the activities of the Institute of Pacific Relations in an effort to maintain peaceful relations between East and West. For his efforts along these lines, he was decorated with the Third Class Order of the Sacred Treasure in 1935 by the Emperor of Japan. He served as department head of the Stanford history department from 1922-1929, and, even after his retirement from teaching in 1945, he remained active in the Stanford community.
Description of the Collection
This collection contains papers of Payson J. Treat from 1907 through 1945. Boxes one and two primarily contain articles and lecture notes written by Treat on issues relating to the Far East. Box one also contains correspondence, bibliographies, and other miscellaneous personal documents. Box three contains class lecture notes from the classes that Professor Treat taught at Stanford and elsewhere. Box four contains business documents relating to the books Treat collected for the Hoover Library. Boxes five through eight (an addition added to the collection in 2004) contain papers by students in Treat's classes; they are arranged first chronologically then alphabetically by author. Box eight also contains a few miscellaneous publications, not by Treat. This collection pertains largely to Payson Treat's teaching career; there is an additional collection of Treat's papers in the Hoover Institution Archives.
Access Terms
Stanford University. Department of History. Students.; Stanford University. Libraries.; Treat, Payson J. (Payson Jackson), 1879-1972; East Asia--Study and teaching.; World War, 1914-1918 --Study and teaching.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Asian Immigrants and Racism. Articles and lectures, 1913-1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Australia and Malaysia. Articles and lectures, 1920-1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - China - Culture and Commerce. Articles and lectures, 1914-1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - China - Foreign Relations and Manchuria. Articles and lectures, 1920-1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - China - Internal Politics and Rebellions. Articles and lectures, 1912-1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Commencement speeches and Stanford talks and lectures, 1910-1919 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, bibliographies, book reviews and papers regarding sabbatical, 1910-1919 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Far East - Miscellaneous. Articles and lectures, 1913-1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - India. Articles and lectures, ca. 1920 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Japan - Culture. Articles and lectures, 1920s-30s, 1920-1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Japan - Foreign Relations and Government. Articles and lectures, 1910s-20s, 1910-1929 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Japan - Rise of New Japan. Articles and lectures, ca. 1921 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Japan - Treaties and World War 1. Articles and lectures, ca. 1918 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Military in a democracy. Articles and lectures, ca. 1917 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous and incomplete documents (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper clippings re Far East, 1917, 1919, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Opium. Articles and lectures, ca. 1927 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Philippines. Articles and lectures (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Trade with the Far East. Articles and lectures, ca. 1920 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - US - Japanese Relations. Articles and lectures, 1910s-20s, 1910-1919 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - US - Miscellaneous Issues. Articles and lectures, ca. 1920 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - US - Relations with the Far East. Articles and lectures, 1910s-30s, 1910-1939 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - War Talks, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - World War 1. Articles and lectures, 1916-1919 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - World War I, Chronology (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Class lecture notes. Hist 9 and 9b, 1907-08, 1907-1908 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Class lecture notes. Hist 21,22,23,1910-1914 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Class lecture notes. Hist 27 and 28,1917-18, 1917-1918 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Class lecture notes. Hist 40 and 92, 1919-20, 1919-1920 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Class lecture notes. Hist 113 and 114, 1931, 1938-39, 1944-45, 1938-1939, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Class lecture notes. Hist 165, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Class lecture notes. Hist 166 and 167, 1924-45, 1924-1945 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Lecture in Geology: Movement of Peoples (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous classes. Lecture notes: Harvard: Philippine Islands, 1909, Univ. of California: Political Sc. 106,1916, Location unknown: War Issues I, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Bibliographies and letters re book purchases (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Hoover Library - letters and documents (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Hoover-Mitchell Fund, Book lists and financial accounts (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Jewel and Syllabus Funds, book lists and library orders (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Library orders (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Syllabus and Jewel Funds, library orders, etc. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Kobayashi, K. "Pol. Sci. 204 Report" n .d. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Lee, Beatrice, "The Manchurian Factors In the Causes of the Russo- Japanese War" n.d. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Luce, Erma, "The Secret Agreements Between Japan, Her Allies, and China. 1917.1918" n.d. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - McLachlan, Anita Jean, "Insurrections In the Philippines Under the Spanish Rule" 1911 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Davis, Jillian, "Chinese Grant of Extraterritoriality to Citizens of the United States in China" 1912 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Eyer, Marjueriti, "The Missionary Problems in China" 1912 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Holt, Suezetta, "The Diplomatic Services of Mr. Pruyn in Japan 1862-5" 1914 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Bryant, Mrs. Albert G., "The Currency Question In Japan 1859-62" 1915 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Bordwell, Helen, "The Japanese Tariff Revision in 1911" 1916 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Sun, Fo, "Chinese Foreign Relations During the Revolutionary Period" 1916 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Wilcox, Lucy, "Sino-Japanese Relations Between 1868 and 1894" 1920 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Willis, Frances E., "Sino-Japanese Relations 1914-1915" 1920 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Gardner, Anna M., "The German Occupation of Kiaowchow" 1921 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Borba, Harry J ., "The Beginnings of Russian Interests In Manchuria 1895-1900" 1923 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Cameron, Meredith E., "Early Contemporary Accounts of the Kow-Tow" 1924 (1 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Cameron, Meredith E., "Relations Between Japan and Korea From 1868 Through 1876" 1924 (2 of2) (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Clyde, Paul H., "A Physical and Political Background for the Study of International Rivalries in Manchuria, Known to the Chinese as the 'Three Eastern Provinces '" 1924 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Osborn, Clarence G., "The Fall of Feudalism In Japan" 1924 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Sloss, Richard L., "The Manchurian Treaty and Notes of 1915" 1924 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Ferguson, Kenneth, "Japanese Interests In Korea From 1876-1884" 1925 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Sheperd, Frances E., "Russian Policy In Korea 1895 to 1903" 1925 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Evans, Luther Harris, "The Dyarchy In the Indian Provinces 1920-1925" 1926 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Kawai, Kazuo, "The Effect of Okubo's Mission to China in 1874 on the Status of the Liukiu Islands" 1926 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Nauman, Patrice, "The Occupation of Kiaochow by Germany" 1926 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Urner, Philip S., "The Annexation of Korea" 1926 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Wright, Robert E., "The Reforms and Progress of Japan In Korea 1905- 1910" 1926 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Arnoldson, Astrid H., "France and the Russo-Japanese War of 1904-1905" 1927 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Probasco, Barbara, "American Public Opinion and the Treaty of Portsmouth" 1927 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Rose, Alice M., "The Annexation of Korea" 1927 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Smith, Dan T., "The Silk Industry of Japan and the Export Trade (A Critical Bibliography)" 1927 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Sloss, Frank H., "The French Sphere of Influence in China. 1894-1902" 1929 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Duryea, Helena, "Prince Ito's Administration and the Korean-Japanese Agreement of 1907" 1930 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Farrier, George Franklin, "Foreign Relations of China During the Year 1914" 1930 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - McClintock, John c., "The Annexation of Korea By Japan" 1930 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - McClintock, Robert Mills, "The Russo-Japanese Struggle For Korea From The Conclusion of the Three-Power Intervention Until The Outbreak of Hostilities; 1895-1904" 1931 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Eisner, Helen, "Korea and the Mongols" 1932 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Hewlett, Marion, "Untitled" 1932 (1 of 2) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Hewlett, Marion, "The Japanese Invasion of Korea: The First Phase" 1932 (20f2) (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Merrill, John E., "The Three Kingdoms and Their Neighbors" 1932 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Nichols, Clare, "China and the Japanese Invasion of Korea" 1932 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Nugent, Dan, "The Japanese-Korean Treaties of 1904, 1905, and 1907" 1932 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Smith, Nicol, " The Japanese Invasion of Korea; The Second Phase" 1932 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Flor, Mary A., "Manchurian Independence Movements to the Establishment of Manchokuo, 1932" 1934 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Flor, Mary Aurel, "The Siberian Intervention ofthe Allied Forces in 1918- '20" 1935 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Muni, Dorothy, "Raffles and Daendals, A Comparison" 1935 (1 of2) (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Muni, Dorothy, "Boycotts; Latest Style" 1935 (2 of2) (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - McClintock, Betty, "The British Participation In the Siege and Relief of the Peking Legations in 1900" 1936 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Turner, Janet, "The Tuchunate In China, 1918-1919" 1936 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Thomas, Charles W., "The United States Army Troops In China 1912- 1937" 1937 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Everett, Norris E., "The Establishment of the Republic of China From the Revolution of 1911 Until the Death of Yuan Shih-Kai June 6,1916" 1938 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Mitchell, Warren Wm, "Diplomatic Negotiations Before and During the Invasion of Korea By Japan, 1592-1598" 1940 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Smith, Kenneth, "The Motives, Purposes, and Preparations of Hideyoshi F or the Invasion of the Continent" 1940 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Buckhout, Blanchard, "Activities of Foreign Troops in North China 1917- 1925" 1941 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Geraldine Boys, The "The Race Equality Controversy at Versailles" 1942 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Haylett, Clarice, "The Secret Russo-Chinese Negotiations 1900-1903" 1943 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, some pertaining to Peter Coutts (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Publications (1 of 3) "The Chinese Social and Political Science Review" and supplement (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Publications (2 of 3) "Address of Dr. Rentaro Mizuno" (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Publications (3 of 3) "The New Leader: Communist China Power and Prospects" (Box 8, Folder 9)